So let’s take a look at the structure of
paradise as it’s presented in Genesis.
So the first aspect of the initial paradaisal
state is un-selfconsciousness.
Now if you look and factor analytic studies
of human personality you note that self-consciousness
although it is arguably our greatest gift
also loads almost entirely on the factor that
defines negative affect.
And you might also notice that when you say,
I became self-conscious you generally put
a negative cast on that in that I was talking
before a group of people and suddenly I was
seized by self-consciousness.
And as a consequence of that I was flooded
by negative emotion and was fundamentally
immobilized.
So it’s a very paradoxical, a very paradoxical
state of being, our highest rational gift
say, and the only on that clearly distinguishes
us from animals is also that which, when manifested,
makes us almost unbearable anxious
The initial paradaisal state when Adam and
Eve first walked in the Garden of Eden is
characterized by an animal-like unselfconsciousness.
Adam and Eve, whatever they are, are not clearly
segregated from the rest of the world.
They have no idea, for example, of their own
nakedness.
And if you think about what nakedness means,
you immediately understand that that’s also
a very profound, dramatic representation.
You know with children around the age of 3
or 4, many of them regardless of their mode
of upbringing, start to become very concerned
about privacy, say with regard to bodily functions
and also very concerned about ever showing
themselves without clothing
and it’s perfectly reasonable to presume
that that’s a consequence of their emergent
self-consciousness, an event that takes place
somewhere between the ages of 2 and 5 and
that’s a defining moment that makes them
segregatable, say from their mother.
And so you also have images of Paradise that
flow through Western history that are characterized
by the image of the unconscious union between
the mother and child
which is an imagistic representation that
eradicates the tension of self-consciousness
both for the mother and for the child.
So the notion that the child is living in
a paradaisal condition that is somehow lost
as he or she approaches adulthood gives another
sort of symbolic layer to the notion of the
pre-selfconscious paradise.
It’s also a place where order and chaos
are in perfect balance
and you know that because what paradise means
is para – around, daisa – a wall, while
Eden means delight or a place of delight.
Paradaisa, paradise is a walled garden, a
walled place of delight
and a garden is precisely that place where
the forces of nature or chaos and the forces
of culture are held in perfect balance, right?
That’s what a garden is.
It’s nature given form by culture and it’s
a place that’s archetypically pleasant a
place where the intervention of human activity
has produced a kind of stability that transcends
that of nature because it’s a cultural construct
but also that transcends that of culture because
all of the plants and the other growing things
that constitute a garden are somehow transcendent
even though they’re under the cultivating
hand of culture and the individual.
If you look at the manner in which the fall
story is represented, you can also see that
the place of craziest stability can be regarded
as a kind of paradise.
So if you remember the story of Moses leading
his people through the desert, it’s clearly
the case that when the Israelites were in
the desert, even though they got away from
the tyranny it was easy to look back and say
well you know, tough as it was, the place
that we were before was much better than the
place we are now.
So it’s perfectly reasonable and expectable
for people who are caught in a crisis to look
back to the time prior to the dawn of that
crisis with longing even if the crisis that
they’re presently experiencing is a necessary
precondition for further development of personality.
So the story that’s laid out in Genesis
has its structure something like this.
Before we became self-conscious the world
was perfect.
As a consequence of the rise of self-consciousness
we were thrown out of the Garden of Eden,
out of paradise and destined to live the profane
existence that characterizes our present mode
of being where we’re subject to knowledge
of mortality and the possibility of Illness
and alienation from God.
And wouldn’t it be ever so great if we could
only return to that condition of unself-consciousness
and make all our problems go away.
And you see this kind of pathological paradaisal
reminiscence manifesting itself in the most
banal forms of conservatism which are always
projecting the ideal – the ideal path somewhere
back into the unattainable reaches of time.
And also in those situations that obtain psychologically
when people are absolutely possessed by depression
and anxiety and wish for their consciousness
to come to an end if not metaphorically so
they desire to sleep, then actually so that
suicide is viewed as a kind of unconsciousness
whose paradaisal nature, the absence of all
opposition, is viewed as clearly preferable
to the difficulties of actually maintaining
being.
Eliade says, the idea of paradise once and
then paradise lost is not something unique
to Western or great Eastern societies.
It’s a widespread motif, just as wide as
the flood motif.
Regardless of where you go in the world you
find this notion.
“When heaven had been abruptly separated
from the earth, that is when it had become
remote as in our days, when the tree or vine
connecting earth to heaven had been cut or
the mountain which used to touch the sky had
been flattened out then the paradaisal stage
was over and man entered into his present
fallen condition.
In effect all myths of paradise show us primordial
man enjoying a beatitude, a spontaneity and
freedom which he has unfortunately lost in
consequence of the fall.
That is of what followed upon a mythical event
that caused the rupture between heaven and
earth.”
As I said, Eden is delight, a place of delight,
by terminological definition whereas paradise
is a walled garden.
I want to show you what knowing that does
for analysis of the relationship between eastern
and western thought.
So let me tell you quickly the story of the
Buddha and I’m going to represent it fundamentally
like this.
Buddha starts his life in what’s essentially
a walled garden by all – by all reasonable
comparative analysis.
And as a consequence of his emergent self-consciousness,
the unself-conscious child-like perfection
of that early state is permanently disrupted
so you have a situation where the greatest
redemption story of the East follows precisely
the same dramatical tract as the greatest
creation story of the West.
So this is the story.
Buddha’s father is visited by an angel who
tells him that his son is going to grow up
to be the greatest temporal profane ruler
the world has ever seen or a great spiritual
leader.
And his father, being a pragmatic and conservative
man, decides that there’s no possible way
I’m going to allow my son to take the ambivalent
road of spiritual enlightenment.
I’m going to allow him to fall completely
in love with the world so that he will remain
attached to this domain.
So prior to Buddha’s birth, his father constructed
a great city with walls around it and inside
that city he removes all signs of pain, frustration
and disappointment, any sign of ugliness and
age, the only people who are allowed to exist
within this city, are those who are in perfect
mental and physical health, who are paragons
of beauty and virtue.
And the idea that lurks behind that archetypal
story is that when a father has a child his
moral obligation is to shield the developing
consciousness of that child from contact with
any of the horrors of life that could provide
the child with an experience too traumatic
for that developing consciousness to apprehend.
So because it’s an archetypal story it relates
to the development of all people, not just
the redemptive saviour and that’s the motif
that the Buddhist story initially follows.
A good father makes his father fall in love
with life by enticing that child into a direct
relationship with all that life has to offer.
So Buddha grows up within this walled garden,
this unselfconscious paradise.
But precisely because he’s being shielded
to this degree and allowed to mature, his
consciousness continues to expand and the
world outside the boundaries that his parents
have established for him starts to attract
his attention.
Now we know already that the forbidden fruit,
right, the lure of what’s outside the walls
is something that human beings just can’t
keep their mangy little paws off, right?
We are absolutely uncontrollably curious and
the best way to make sure that we investigate
something is to lay down a structure that
says, whatever you do under whatever circumstances
never look there, right?
And then the automatic systems that underlie
our orienting and that motivate our seeking
experience are constantly pulling our attention
precisely to that forbidden spot, compelling
us to investigate exactly that which has been
forbidden.
So because Buddha is a consciousness developing
in a healthy manner he immediately becomes
curious about what lies beyond the limits
that have been established with him and he
makes a decision to go outside of paradise.
right, which seems a particularly ridiculous
thing to do, given that in principle he had
everything he could possibly want inside the
walls.
But then again we have the troublesome notion
of the original sin of Adam, right, which
is that if any of you were offered a forbidden
fruit again under circumstances mythologically
equivalent to those that obtained in the beginning,
you’d immediately reach your hand out and
take it because what we haven’t got for
human beings is always far more compelling
than what we have got
So Buddha goes outside the walls.
But his father, who’s a good father although
somewhat conservative, decides he’s going
to rig the game a little bit so he gets rid
of everybody that’s diseased or unhappy
or uncomfortable or ugly or old or anything
that could possibly disturb the Buddha.
and he lines the streets with flower waving
women and puts petals on the road and sends
his son out in a gilded chariot.
But the gods who are lurking around, right,
the trouble making gods who represent chaos
and disorder and the unknown decide to send
in front of Buddha a sick man who hobbles
unsteadily into view.
and Buddha asks his retainer precisely what
this phenomena represents and his retainer
says, well you know, human beings like you
since you’re human are subject to the deterioration
of these mere physical powers in an arbitrary
way.
And this man is one person who’s been so
afflicted.
And so Buddha is completely disenchanted by
his exploratory move out into the terrible
unknown and runs back into the castle walls
and shuts the door and is perfectly happy
to think of nothing for months.
But then as his anxiety habituates and his
curiosity grows, he can’t stand the notion
of never going outside the walls again and
outside he goes again.
And this time after his father prepares the
route ever so carefully the gods send inside
an old man who hobbles into view.
And Buddha look at him in shock and horror
and says to his retainer, just precisely what’s
going on here?
And his retainer says, well that’s an old
man.
Everybody gets old and you’re going to get
old too and that’s the way of all humanity.
And that’s the point at which Buddha’s
self-consciousness expands not to only include
the possibility of degeneration but to include
the temporal horizon that’s characteristic
of life.
And he finds that so terribly shocking that
he runs back into the castle and shuts the
walls down and plays with his friends for
another six months until his anxiety, or maybe
a year, until his anxiety finally habituates
and he goes out one final time.
And this time the gods send a funeral parade
for him and he sees his first dead body.
And this such a terrible shock to him that
he can’t even go back to the castle.
So his father prepares for him a great party
in the woods near the castle full of nude
dancing women who are perfectly willing to
flaunt themselves and to offer themselves
to him.
But Buddha is so absolutely and catastrophically
shocked by this notion of emergent death that
he can’t take any pleasure whatsoever in
what’s being offered to him and he leaves
the kingdom once and for all.
And you think, well that’s exactly what
happens to you when you grow up, right?
If you’re reasonably well socialized and
properly looked after then your curiosity
gets the better of you and you keep going
out into the world until what your parents
have established for you is no longer sufficient
for you.
And as a consequence of that movement out
into the world, you find out all sorts of
things characteristic of your own life that
not only your parents can’t precisely explain
to you but even the broader formal structures
of your culture have a very difficult time
handling.
And when you finally do encounter such realities
and allow their effect on you to fully manifest
itself well then you’re finally independent
and you no longer can return home.
But from that point forward you’re also
burdened as Adam is burdened when he loses
his paradaisal unself-consciousness with the
full revelation of what it means to be limited
and alive.
So what happens to Buddha as a consequence
of this revelation?
He becomes an apprentice and the chronicles
of the Buddha’s adventure are careful to
say that he becomes the world’s most proficient
practitioner of Samkhya, which was a philosophical
precursor to yoga and then to yoga.
So he masters all the positions and the asanas
until he’s disciplined physically to an
almost unlimited degree.
And then he decides that he’ll adopt a stance
of world renunciation which is also something
he’s remarkably good at.
And he starves himself until the chroniclers
say he resembles nothing so much as a pile
of dust.
And then, having exhausted all the disciplinary
structures that his sophisticated culture
has to offer him but still not precisely finding
the answer that he’s looking for, he retreats
into the forest, place of the unknown, and
sits himself at the base of a tree.
Underneath the tree he’s visited by visions
and temptations.
The first vision is an essentially erotic
one.
Life itself tempts him back out of his self-conscious
state into the domain of pure physical pleasure,
a perfectly reasonable temptation, right,
and one that’s powerful enough so that Hindu
philosophers say as their churches and cathedrals
are covered with erotic drawings, if you can’t
get past the erotic drawings into the church
that’s the domain that you should still
inhabit, right.
In the dawning phases of life at least till
middle age that’s the appropriate mode of
being to be enticed and seduced by the physical
pleasures that life has to offer.
But in the final analysis those are not sufficient
to solve the problem of emergent self-consciousness.
And so the angel of death visits him and offers
him the opportunity to exist permanently in
a state of nirvana.
A very, very interesting twist on the story
because you have to wonder, given the association
say between suicidelity and the notion of
paradise that exists underneath that, if what
Buddha isn’t being offered by the angel
of death is in fact death and the cessation
of all the problems of being regardless he
rejects that, attains enlightenment briefly
and then decides to return to the world to
share what he’s discovered with all of suffering
humanity.
The idea being that the Buddha who is the
awakened or enlightened one is capable of
attaining a transcendent state but also knows
fully that because human beings have a shared
social aspect it is not possible for any one
person to attain redemption until all people
attain redemption, the reason being that it’s
very difficult to be transcendent and enlightened
when you see someone who’s sick lying in
a ditch.
So then we shift from that back to Genesis
and the tempted fall of man and read the third
chapter.
And they were both naked, the man and his
wife and were not ashamed.
Well what does that mean?
Well, Freud pointed out that one of human
being’s most common nightmares is to be
stripped of clothing in front of a crowd.
Now why would that be precisely?
Well your naked self is the most vulnerable
aspect of you, right?
We’re all clothed and for good reason.
Partly that’s protection from the terrible
natural world, right?
But it also offers us the possibility of placing
a barrier between ourselves, our vulnerable
selves and the searching and critical gaze
of the community, right?
Because not only are we vulnerable to the
rigours of nature, we’re also vulnerable
to the depredations and criticisms of society.
And the notion that a man and a woman could
exist naked and not know it is a clear – is
a clear finger pointing in the direction of
a story that says these people were not conscious
or if conscious they certainly were not self-conscious.
And how does the story develop?
"The serpent was more subtle than any beast
of the field which the Lord God had made.
And he said unto the woman: yea, hath God
said you shall not eat of every tree in the
Garden.
And the woman said unto the serpent, well
we may eat of the fruit of the trees of the
Garden but of the fruit of the tree which
is in the centre of the Garden God has said
you should not eat of it, neither shall you
touch it lest ye die.
And the serpent said to the woman: you won’t
die for God knows that in the day you eat
thereof then your eyes shall be opened, right,
a clear pointing to the notion of an awakening
and an illumination-- And ye shall be like
gods knowing good and evil,"
right, which attributes to humanity, a dawning
sense of morality explicit morality, the faculty
for comprehension that we do not share with
any other animal.
"And when the woman saw that the tree was
good for food and that it was pleasant to
the eyes and a tree to be desired to make
one wise, she took of the fruit thereof and
did eat and gave also unto her husband with
her and he did eat.
"
Women, trouble.
What’s the tree?
Well we talked about this a little bit before.
So you say, well if you look at the structure
of experience from this particular perspective
and you think about that in a horizontal plane,
vertical plane, sorry, with the layers one
on top of another, then you can imagine the
tree as the thing that unites these three
layers.
The tree is the domain that unites chaos and
order and the individual, the structure running
up through the middle of it.
And you see a representation of that interestingly
enough, from Norse mythology.
This is the Yggdrasill the axis mundi the
tree of the gods, the tree that stands in
the middle of the Norse paradise.
And one of the things that’s very interesting
about this particular tree is that if you
look at its roots the roots are covered with
snakes and serpents and underneath the snakes
and serpents is water.
And so that you see that the tree that stands
at the centre of the world is rooted in chaos
fundamentally, is rooted in whatever it is
that constitutes the pre-cosmogonic matrix
of being.
And then the central aspects of this domain
are nicely laid out as the domain of territoriality,
the ends of the borders that the individual
understands and the habitual territory that
he inhabits and then the tree in the centre
represents whatever it is that’s central
to this – to our mode of being.
And so let’s take a look at that in some
detail and flesh it out symbolically.
We find Eliade is saying the tree that stands
hypothetically at the centre of the world
is precisely that structure that shamans climb
when they make their transition from normal
mode of earthly being into their transcendent
mode of being.
So Eliade says the symbolism of the ascension
into heaven by means of a tree is clearly
illustrated by the ceremony of initiation
of a Buryat shaman.
The candidate climbs up a post in the middle
of his yurt, his tent, reaches the summit
and goes out by the smoke hole.
But we know that this opening made to let
out the smoke is likened to the hole made
by the pole star in the bulk of heaven.
So you can imagine there’s a conceptualization
of the world as centred around a particular
axis and that the tent is regarded as, at
least transitorily as a symbolic equivalent
of the cosmological structure.
Among other peoples the tent hole is called
the pillar of the sky and is compared to the
pole star around which the world rotates,
at least from the visual perspective and is
named elsewhere the nail of the sky.
Thus, the ritual post set up in the middle
of the yurt is an image of the cosmic tree
which is found at the centre of the world
with the pole star shining directly above
it.
By ascending it, the candidate enters into
heaven.
That is why as soon as he comes out of the
smoke hole of the tent he gives a loud cry
invoking the help of the gods Up there he
finds himself in their presence.
The tree is an absolutely archaic symbol and
it seems to me most likely that it represents
the structure of the nervous system.
I think a structure that’s rooted not so
much in the spinal, sensory motor structures
but deeply in the autonomic structures, stretching
down into the centre of the body and planting
the mind firmly in its material substrate
so that the autonomic system and its projections
up into the amigdylla and limbic system and
then up into the cortex constitute the interface
between the spiritual domain that our psyche
inhabits and the material domain that constitutes
our body.
The tree at the centre of our being.
What does the tree do?
Well it bears fruit.
Well what sort of fruit?
Well there are multiple medieval representations
that are quite peculiar showing Christ, for
example, as the fruit of the tree of the knowledge
of good and evil.
The fruit of the tree of life.
And what does that mean?
It means that conceptualizations like the
hero are the products of whatever it is that
this tree represents.
The tree is something that produces fruit.
Fruit is also something that can be ingested.
And as Eric Newman points out wherever liquor,
fruit, herbs, etc. appear as the vehicles
of life and immortality, including the water
and bread of life, the sacrament of the host
and every form of food cult down to the present
day we have an ancient mode of human expression
before us.
So imagine the idea of the – of the Piagetian
idea of assimilation and then accommodation
and then understand its assimilative, nutritive,
underlying metaphorical nature.
The idea being that there’s a tight analogy
between ingesting something material and undergoing
a transformation of energy.
Attendant upon that, right, which is what
happens when you eat and ingesting a piece
of information which offers you a new mode
of doing things so you can say well people
will trade work for information.
They will trade food for information.
There must be a kind of equivalence between
work and information and food and information
because otherwise the trade wouldn’t make
sense.
And then you realize that if you’re informed
you can undertake transformations of yourself
and the material world in a much more efficient
manner because that’s what being informed
means.
And that means that being informed, acquiring
some information and eating something are
all tied up in a complex way into the same
metaphorical structure.
Eat something forbidden, transform as a consequence.
Conscious realization is acted out in the
elementary scheme of nutritive assimilation
and a ritual act of concrete eating is the
first assimilation known to man.
Conscious realization is acted out through
ritual by an act of eating.
Since the act of eating represents a very
familiar example of assimilation.
The assimilation and ingestion of the content,
the eaten food, produces an inner change.
Transformation of the body cell through food
intake is the most elementary of animal changes
experienced by man.
How a weary, enfeebled and famished man can
be turned into an alert, strong and satisfied
being or a man perishing of thirst can be
refreshed or even transformed by an intoxicating
drink.
This is and must remain a fundamental experience
so long a man shall exist.
Eric Newman’s point being that our psychological
experience of the capacity of psychological
transformation through eating is a metaphor
waiting to be applied to the equivalent experience
that we obtain, the equivalent excitement
and sense of transformative possibility that
we acquire as a consequence of coming across
some new and truly valuable piece of information.
So you have the idea that the tree that stands
at the centre of the world, the individual
mode of being, is something that bears fruit.
And the ingestion of that fruit, that idea
say or that piece of information is something
that can produce a permanent transformation.